In the beginning, it was an orb.
（観察者）それは初め“球(きゅう)”だった
Not just any orb.
ただの球ではない
It was an orb that captured the reflections
of many things and changed in response.
ありとあらゆるものの姿を
写しとり
変化することができる
I decided to cast the orb unto
the Earth and observe it.
私は それを この地に投げ入れ
観察することにした
It spent some time in the form of a rock.
それは しばらく
石の姿になって過ごした
（雷と豪雨）
As its surroundings grew warmer,
it took the form of moss.
（観察者）暖かくなると
今度は苔(こけ)を写しとった
In time, snow began to fall upon the land.
やがて この地に
雪が降り始めた
（吹雪）
A Reshy wolf appeared from the south...
１匹のレッシオオカミが
南方から現れ…
and then it perished.
そして力尽きた
It then took on the form of the wolf.
それは
オオカミの姿になった
（遠吠え）
And it became conscious.
（観察者）そして意識を獲得した
It didn't know how to walk, but it was
soon able to replicate the behavior.
歩き方を知らなかったが
すぐに再現することができた
（鳴き声）
It moved clumsily.
動きが鈍い
傷口も複製したらしい
It seemed to have replicated
the wolf's injury.
Its first discomfort.
初めての不快感 初めての痛み
Its first pain.
But it recovered within twenty seconds.
しかし20秒かけて回復
Not a problem.
問題はない
It began to walk,
それは歩き始めた
experiencing the cold of the wind and
the scent of the snow for the first time
初めて感じる風の冷たさや
雪のニオイを覚えながら
as it wandered aimlessly.
あてもなく…
（鳴子の音）
Joaan!
（少年）ジョアン!?
やっと帰ってきた！
You're finally back!
Thank goodness you're safe!
よかった 無事で
You were gone for two whole
months! I was so worried!
心配してたんだぞ
２か月も帰らないから
But I knew you'd never forget about me.
君が僕のこと忘れるなんて
ありえないもんな
You seem quieter than usual.
ん？　お前…
いつもより おとなしいな
I get it. You must be tired.
そうかそうか 疲れたか
（ジョアンの鼻息）
Here, there were many
new and unfamiliar things.
（観察者）そこには
知らないものが たくさんあった
（ジョアンの鼻息）
The pleasure it felt as its
body temperature rose,
体温が上がる気持ちよさと
（薪が燃える音）
an unidentifiable scent...
得体の知れない香り
魅力的な空間
This was an alluring space.
If it could speak, it would have said
it wanted to stay here forever.
もしも口をきけるなら
“ずっと ここにいたい”と
言っただろう
（ジョアン）バウ！
I keep telling you not to go near the fire.
（少年）火に近づいちゃダメだって
いつも言ってるだろ
Here's your food.
はい ゴハン
（ニオイを嗅ぐ音）
クゥ
ん？
Here.
ほら
Huh?
あれ？
I get it.
分かった
You don't like it because
it's not horndeer milk.
気に食わないんだな
ツノジカのミルクじゃないから
Well, I can't help that.
でも仕方ないだろ
The last one died a year ago.
最後のは
もう１年も前に死んだんだし
The fire's going out.
そろそろ火が消える
We should go to sleep before it does.
冷える前に寝ようか ん？
This boy, whose name it didn't even
know, was the first person it met.
（観察者）
名前も知らぬ その少年が
それが出会った最初の１人だった
The Last One
（オノの音）
ふんっ
It's never going to dry if it keeps snowing.
雪続きで ちっとも乾燥しない
The wood from Auntie's place is no good.
おばさん家(ち)の木はダメダメだな
What's that? I have no right to complain
when I'm taking people's stuff?
人ん家(ち)から拝借しといて
そりゃないだろって？
Sorry. I know.
ごめん 分かってるよ
Everyone's going to be
angry when they get back.
みんなが帰ってきたら
怒られちゃうね
What choice do I have?
仕方ないだろう？
こうでもしないと僕が死んじまうよ
I have to do this, or I'll die.
Of course I believe it!
当たり前だ！
みんなが出ていって５年
It's been five years since they left.
Only five years!
まだ５年だ
I mean, they're way past there.
だって あの向こう
ずっとずーっと向こうなんだぞ
Way, way over there.
（風が吹く）
There's lots of food and people there.
そこには たくさんの人や
食べ物があって
They all went because they believed that.
みんな それを信じて…
あ… フッ
And you know what?
They told me it's like paradise there.
そこはね みんなが言うには
まるで楽園のような場所さ
There's plenty of fish, and lots of tasty stuff called... "fruit," I think?
魚は たくさんいるし
おいしいクダモノ？
ってやつが いっぱいあるんだって
There are tons of people who
are way smarter than we are,
そこには僕らより
ずっと賢い人たちがいて
and they all live happily
together every day.
毎日 幸せに暮らしてるんだ
I'm so jealous.
いいな 僕も行きたかった
I wish I could've gone.
Do you remember?
覚えてる？　僕 大人たちと
出ていこうとしたけど
I tried to go with the grown-ups,
but I couldn't, because you stopped me.
お前に止められて失敗したんだよな
You bit my leg.
足かまれてさ
So they told me I had to stay behind and
watch over Grandma and the old folks.
それで“ばーさんたちの
面倒見てろ”って留守番になって
Isn't that awful?
ひどいよな
They said they'd be back with
gifts once they found paradise.
“楽園を見つけたら手土産 持って
帰ってくる”って言ったのに…
Remember when they said that?
言ったのにな？
In the end, the only ones who stayed behind
were the old folks that I couldn't save...
結局ここに残ったのは
僕が助けてあげられなかった
おばあさんたちと
and us.
僕ら…
（鳴子の音）
あっ！
Joaan!
ジョアン！
あ…
フゥ フゥ フゥ…
フゥ フゥ…
Please...
お願いします
Welcome home!
おかえり！
（鳴子の音）
Just kidding! It was actually a fish!
なーんてね！　魚でした
Woo-hoo! We haven't had one this big in ages!
やったー 久々の大物だ
Here's your share.
ほら お前の分
We need to save wood, so let's eat the rest raw.
残りは燃料節約だ
ナマで食おう ん？
（ニオイを嗅ぐ音）
クゥ
What's wrong? That part's your favorite.
どうした？　大好物だろ？
食べ方 忘れたのか？
Have you forgotten how to eat?
Like this!
ほら！
You put it in your mouth and chew.
こうやって…
Munch, munch.
口でモグモグ…
See?
ほら！
ゴグッ… ほら！
See?
あ…
Hey, you can eat.
なんだ 食べれるじゃないか
（少年）ん？
Oh, this is Uncle and Auntie.
ああ これが おじさんとおばさん
And here's my older cousin and his kids,
いとこの兄ちゃんと その子供たち
and the hairy guy from across the street...
お向かいの毛玉じいさん
And this is the lady next door.
Doesn't it look just like her?
これが隣のおばさん 似てるだろ？
I just wanted to make it clear
that there were people here...
ここに人がいたって分かるようにね
and make sure I don't forget.
それと…
忘れないように
Joaan, I'm thinking of
leaving this place, too.
ジョアン 僕もここを出ようと思う
I want to meet all sorts of people
and feel all sorts of things.
いろんな人に会って
いろんなことを感じたいんだ
I'm sure some of it will be bad,
きっと悪いこともあるだろうけど
but I still want to learn about the world.
それでも僕は世界を知りたいんだ
Of course, you're coming with me.
もちろん… 君も一緒だ
（扉が閉まる音）
（鳴き声）
You can't see the sea anymore.
（少年）海が見えなくなった！
I've never come this far before.
ここまで来たの初めてだよ
According to my uncle, it's due south.
おじさんが言うには… 真南！
You turn your back to my house
and just walk straight.
僕の家を背に
まっすぐ進むんだって
You can't see it now,
今は見えないけど いずれ
大きな壁みたいに山が現れて
but eventually, you'll see a huge
mountain standing there like a wall.
Past that is paradise.
その先が楽園さ
All right, let's keep going until it gets dark.
さあ 暗くなるまで進むぞ！
あっ　何だろう？
What's that?
あっ これ メッセージだ！
It's a message!
For people like me who
are heading to paradise!
僕みたいな これから楽園を
目指す人に向けた！
It's saying to go this way!
この方向へ進めって
Yes! This is great!
やった やったぞ！
See, Joaan?
なあ ジョアン
出てきたかいがあったよな？
Aren't you glad we left?
（鳴き声）
Yeah, I'm happy, too!
ああ 僕もうれしいよ
Do you know what vegetables are, Joaan?
ジョアンはヤサイって知ってる？
Apparently, I ate some a long time ago,
but I don't remember it at all.
僕は昔 食べたらしいんだけど
全然 覚えてないんだ
And then there're the round,
sweet things called "fruit."
ほかには丸くて甘いクダモノ
I asked my uncle what "sweet" is like,
but I still didn't really get it.
甘いって どんな感じか
おじさんに聞いたんだけど
よく分かんなかった
I can't wait to try it.
早く食べたいな…
ああ ワクワクする
I'm so excited.
It'll be ultimate freedom!
最高に自由だ！
It's really starting to snow.
雪 降ってきたな
（ジョアン）グウ…
Oh? Was that a whimper I just heard?
おお 今のは弱音か ジョアン？
Our journey's just getting started.
旅は まだ始まったばかりなんだぜ
ん？
あっ えいっ…
Look! It's a tree!
見て 木だよ
すごいぞ　山に近づいてる証拠だ
This is amazing! It means we're
getting close to the mountains!
Let's take some for firewood.
たきぎ用に少し頂こう
There.
よし！
Time to head out again.
再出発… ん？
（少年）わっ
ヘヘ… やっちゃった
Now I've done it...
My face is freezing.
うわー 顔凍る 全部ぬれた
I'm soaked through.
This is great, though! There's a river here!
でもすごい こんな所に川が！
魚釣ろう 魚！
Let's catch some fish!
You just laughed at me, didn't you?
あっ 今笑っただろ お前
ん？
うわ…
（布を裂く音）
That'll do it.
これでよし
Don't worry. I'll be fine.
大丈夫 大丈夫だって
ただの かすり傷
It's just a scratch.
Come on, stop joking around.
おいおい 冗談よせよ
帰らないぞ 僕は
I'm not going back.
That would be way too embarrassing.
そんなカッコ悪いこと できるか
It's not like we're out of food.
食糧が尽きたわけでもないのに
んっ
We're walking tomorrow, too.
明日も歩くからな
あさっても しあさっても
And the day after, and the day after that.
Even if you say you don't want to.
お前がイヤだって言っても歩く
You gotta use your strength
while you still have it.
体力は あるうちに使うもんだ
フゥ
ハァ ハァ ハァ…
That's not right, Joaan.
（少年）それは違うよ ジョアン
I think it would be even
more foolish to give up
みんなが生きているかどうか
分からないから
just because we don't know
if the others are still alive.
進むのをやめるってのは
僕は もっと愚かだと思うよ
Even if we went back now,
we'd just rot away with that house.
このまま帰っても
あの家と一緒に朽ちるだけだ
I don't want that.
そんなの僕はイヤだ
I want to go where the others are.
みんなと同じ場所へ行く
That's the only thing
that's left for me to do.
これくらいしか 僕には
もうやりたいことがないんだ
And I'm sure the reason they haven't come back
is because where they are now is so great.
それに みんなが
帰ってこないのは きっと
その場所が魅力的だから
Great food, great people...
魅力的な食べ物 魅力的な人たち
They're enjoying themselves so much,
and they're having too much fun.
それが すごく楽しくて うれしくて
幸せすぎるんだ だから…
That's why...
ああ…
く…
あっ
This is amazing, Joaan!
これはすごいぞ ジョアン！
This is evidence that
there were people here!
これは人がいた痕跡だ
Look at this!
見てよ ここに
みんながいたってことだ
They really came through here!
Which means, uh...
だから あの…
We're on the right track!
この先で間違いない
このまま山に行ける
We can make it to the mountains!
We can definitely make it!
僕たち絶対に行ける！
We can...
行ける…
うっ く…
Can we... make it?
行ける… かな？
Wh-What do you think, Joaan?
ど… どう思う ジョアン？
Do you think I can make it?
僕 行けると思う？
Tell me.
教えてよ
Say something to me like you always do.
いつもみたいに僕に何か言って
I guess you can't answer me, huh?
答え… られるわけないよな
O-Of course not...
そう… そうだよな
I was just talking to
myself this whole time!
僕は僕と…
会話をしてただけなんだから！
Damn it...
クソッ クソ！
Damn it!
（咳き込む）
ハァハァハァ… ハァ…
Yeah...
そうだね ごめんよ ジョアン
I'm sorry, Joaan.
You came with me all this way.
君はずっと ついてきてくれたのに
こんなこと言って…
I shouldn't have said that.
I'm sorry.
ごめん… ごめんよ
I'm sorry...
Let's go back.
帰ろう
Let's go back, okay, Joaan?
帰ろうか ジョアン
I decided that.
僕が そう決めた 君じゃない
Not you.
I want to go home.
僕が帰りたい
僕は帰りたい 帰ろう
Let's go.
（ジョアンの吠え声）
（少年）うっ あああ…
（少年の泣き声）
（ジョアン）クゥ…
ハハハ 何だよ その顔
Why are you looking at me like that?
うっ ハァ…
Do you feel sick?
具合でも悪いのか？
Or are you trying to make me smile?
それとも僕を
笑わせようとしているのか？
I know, I know.
分かってる分かってる
腹減ってんだろ…
You're hungry, aren't you?
ハハ… 今メシ作ってやるから
I'll make you something to eat.
Good, good.
よしよし 治ってきてる
It's healing.
アハハ
うまそうなニオイでもするか？
Does it smell yummy or something?
Once this wound heals,
we're going to try again, Joaan.
このケガが治ったら もう一回
挑戦だからな ジョアン
フゥ フゥ…
（少年の荒い息）
う… ハァ…
That's... strange...
おかしいな…
（ジョアン）グルル…
（少年）フフ…
（物音）
（少年）ん？　ああ…
My chair...
イス… ん…
ハァ…
Y'know... I... I don't want to be lying down...
ほら…
み… みんなが帰ってきたときに
when everyone gets back. I'd look pathetic.
寝てたら みっともないだろ？
This is my spot.
こだわり…
This is where... I look best.
ここが… カッコいい
Joaan...
ジョアン 僕…
君に お願いがあるんだけど
I want you to do something for me.
Remember me...
僕のこと…
forever.
ずっと覚えていて
（倒れる音）
（ジョアン）キャン！
All right, time to set
out for paradise again!
さあ これで
また楽園 目指せるぞ！
Huh? Joaan!
あれ？　ジョアン！
Everyone!
みんなも！
（ジョアンの鳴き声）
Wow... You were all waiting for me!
そうか 僕を待っててくれたんだね
That's great! I'm not alone anymore!
よかった もう１人じゃない
I can keep going now!
これで僕は がんばれる
Look, everyone! There are people!
見て みんな！　人がいる
Hello, everyone.
こんにちは 皆さん はじめまして
Nice to meet you.
Tell me about this place.
ここは どんな所ですか？
Have you heard of fruit?
クダモノって知ってます？
Hello!
こんにちは はじめまして
僕の名前は…
Nice to meet you!
My name is...
It took on the form of a human.
（観察者）
それは人間の姿を獲得した
Conditions must be met to obtain a new form.
獲得には条件がある
It needs stimulation.
“刺激”である
It set forth in search of more stimulation.
それは さらなる刺激を求めて
歩き出した
It will meet all kinds of people
and feel all kinds of things...
これから先 いろんな人に会って
いろんなことを感じるだろう
Just as the boy had wished to do.
少年が そうしたかったように
♪～
～♪
Preview
It arrived in a great forest.
（観察者）
それが たどり着いたのは
森の大地ニナンナ
The South.
There, a young girl, March, lives freely.
村で のびのびと育つ
幼い少女マーチ
But by the law of the land,
she is chosen to be a sacrifice.
しかし村のしきたりで
いけにえに選ばれ
Her dream of becoming a grown-up
is about to come to an end.
大人になりたいという彼女の夢は
絶たれようとしていた
Two beings striving to
survive meet one another.
生きようと もがく
２つの命が出会う
A Rambunctious Girl